Guide to the William K. Wimsatt Research Files on Alexander Pope and Art
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William K. Wimsatt Research Files on Alexander Pope and Art
1950-1970
OSB MSS 170
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.84
(9 boxes)
The collection contains subject files, printed material, photographs, scrapbooks and slides on the subject of Alexander Pope and art, assembled by eighteenth-century scholar William K. Wimsatt. Much of this material may have been gathered in the course of Wimsatt's research for The Portraits of Alexander Pope (1965).
Wimsatt, William K. (William Kurtz), 1907-1975
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs.William K. Wimsatt, 1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William K. Wimsatt (1907-1975)
William K. Wimsatt was born in Washington, D.C., and educated at Georgetown and at Yale, where he received his doctorate in English in 1939. Wimsatt specialized in eighteenth-century literature, and he spent his entire teaching career in the English Department at Yale, from 1939 until his death in 1975.
Wimsatt's scholarly publications include The Prose Style of Samuel Johnson (1941), Selected Poetry and Prose of Alexander Pope (editor, 1951), Boswell for the Defense (editor, 1959), Samuel Johnson on Shakespeare (editor, 1960), The Portraits of Alexander Pope (1965), and Samuel Johnson: Selected Poetry and Prose (editor, with Frank Brady, 1978). He is perhaps best known, however, as co-author of The Verbal Icon (1954) with Monroe C. Beardsley. This work introduced the concepts of the "intentional fallacy" and the "affective fallacy" to a wide audience, and both quickly became central tenets of the New Criticism.
Wimsatt married Margaret Elizabeth Hecht in 1944, and the couple had two children. His hobbies included painting, playing chess, and collecting Native American artifacts. Wimsatt died in New Haven, Connecticut in 1975.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains subject files, printed material, photographs, scrapbooks and slides on the subject of Alexander Pope and art, assembled by eighteenth-century scholar William K. Wimsatt. Much of this material may have been gathered in the course of Wimsatt's research for The Portraits of Alexander Pope (1965).
Arrangement
Organized into three series. I. Images of Pope, 1950-1970. II. Research Files on Pope and Art. III. Scrapbooks and Slides.
Authors, English -- 18th century -- Portraits; Color slides; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744 -- Portraits; Wimsatt, William K. (William Kurtz), 1907-1975
- Images of Pope, circa 1950-1970; Series I; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Material is unarranged.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains printed and photographic reproductions of sculpture, paintings, and engravings of Alexander Pope, filed with related notes and printed material.
  - Images of Pope, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 1)
  - Images of Pope, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 2)
- Research Files on Pope and Art, [circa 1950-1970]; Series II; 3; (3 boxes)
  Series contains research files on various topics related to Alexander Pope and art, including collecting, provenance, and creation of artwork, and other themes. Files contain manuscript notes, correspondence, printed articles and a few reproductions of images.
  - Research files on Pope and art, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 3)
  - Research files on Pope and art, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 4)
  - Research files on Pope and art, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 5)
- Scrapbooks and Slides, [circa 1950-1970]; Series III; 3.84; (4 boxes)
  Series contains several scrapbooks containing research and notes on images of Alexander Pope and slide reproductions of Pope-related artwork.
  - Scrapbooks, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 7)
  - Slides, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 8)
  - Slides, [circa 1950-1970] (Box 9)